<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
        <title>Beyond LMS</title>
        <description>Beyond LMS - Beyond LMS</description>
        <link>http://beyondlms.org</link>
        <link>http://beyondlms.org</link>
        <lastBuildDate>2015-07-21T20:29:24+02:00</lastBuildDate>
        <pubDate>2015-07-21T20:29:24+02:00</pubDate>
        <ttl>1800</ttl>


        <item>
                <title>xAPI Camp</title>
                <description>
&lt;h6&gt;
	Kirsty Kitto
&lt;/h6&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;
		So today we are &quot;speaking&quot; at &lt;a href=&quot;http://connectionsforum.com/xapi-camp-seattle/&quot;&gt;xAPI Camp&lt;/a&gt;! Not really, I am in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Freiburg_im_Breisgau&quot;&gt;Freiburg&lt;/a&gt; visiting some collaborators for another project, and Aneesha is still in Brisbane, but together with the help of &lt;a href=&quot;http://andrewresearch.net/&quot;&gt;Andrew Gibson&lt;/a&gt; (one of my PhD students, who seems to actually know what he is doing when it comes to making videos... unlike me) we have created a video that will be screened, and will then join in on a twitter discussion (assuming people actully want to tweet to us :) 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		I am hoping this will be interesting. The motivation underlying the video is to try and get the xAPI community moving forwards on a few key initiatives to do with data sharing and portabiity. When asked to write a short paragraph about why I was &quot;attending&quot; xAPI Camp I said that: &quot;&lt;i&gt;I think that xAPI is at a critical juncture, and it is important for the community to reflect upon its purpose at this point. What are we going to do with our xAPI data? Is it just for the managers and HR departments, or are we going to give it to the learner? What kinds of things do we want to report on? I would like to see xAPI data used to enable things like discourse analytics, creativity, metacognition, and life long personalised learning, but in order to do this we need to consider analytics and controlled vocabularies. I am looking forwards to a conversation about data extraction, complex analytics, and learner focused reporting…how can we use the standard to encourage higher order thinking in our learners?&lt;/i&gt;&quot; (see the other presenter paragraphs &lt;a href=&quot;http://risc-inc.com/blog/why-attend-xapi-camp-amazon-part-2/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		I really mean this. Are we playing the same old games here? Or are we going to try and create a new and better data standard? One with the learner at its heart. Wouldn&#39;t it be great if our learners could own their data, and take it with them from School to University to Work? What if they could use it to create their own portfolios of skills and capabilities... and use this to tell a story about their mastery of key knowledge as they mature. There are many ethical and technical issues involved in this kind of vision. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		To me, the biggest ethical ones are all to do with data ownership and the right to be forgotten... should the enormous fight (about his pedagogy of all things!) that I had with my Electromagnetism and Relativity lecturer at age 20 show up as an indicator for &quot;aggression&quot; when I am 40? This fight resulted in my later failure of the course (not directly because of him... I just stopped participating), but then there is the HD I got the next year. I think it would be a terrible thing if these kinds of records became even more widely available then they currently are, but the age of data collection is upon us, and I think we owe it to ourselves and each other to behave very responsibly here. (Far more than we have so far.) I am tired of listening to that certain subset of &quot;baby boomers&quot; who never really understood data talking about how &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marcprensky.com/writing/Prensky%20-%20Digital%20Natives,%20Digital%20Immigrants%20-%20Part1.pdf&quot;&gt;digital natives&lt;/a&gt;&quot; don&#39;t care if we collect data about them. If you ask them the right way they patently do... in fact some of them have a very sophisticated notion of data ownership. So that is one set of issues... hard ones, but I do think that a data ownership model goes some way towards alleviating them... although this opens up its own technical issues as &lt;a href=&quot;http://connectionsforum.com/vimeo-video/ben-betts-on-personal-data/&quot;&gt;Ben Betts talks about at another xAPI Camp&lt;/a&gt;. I have been asked to write a blog for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.laceproject.eu/&quot;&gt;LACE project&lt;/a&gt; about this, so will most definitely put my musings about it down here at some point when things calm down. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		In my view, the biggest technical issues stem from data portability, and this is the key focus of the video. We are introducing the CLA toolkit, which means that we get to talk about xAPI, recipes, data extraction, and finally analytics... and paint a picture about how these all fit together in the more complex use cases that this kind of lifelong data ownership model would require. Have a watch of the video and see what you think (sorry - posting it after the event ;). I might try to generate a summary of the Twitter conversation (if anything emerges) in a couple of days in a follow up blog.
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;





</description>
                <link>http://beyondlms.org/blog/21/07/2015/xAPICamp</link>
                <guid>http://beyondlms.org/blog/21/07/2015/xAPICamp</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-21T00:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>How should we teach in the wild? (Infrastructure and Swiss Wanderwegs)</title>
                <description>
&lt;h6&gt;
	Kirsty Kitto
&lt;/h6&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		So, for the last week or so I was in Switzerland. I had a conference to attend in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filzbach&quot;&gt;Filzbach&lt;/a&gt;, but coming from Australia, you are braver than me if you don&#39;t try to arrive at least a couple of days before you have to deal with sitting in a room all day.. jetlag meas that I almost inevitably end up falling asleep after lunch if I don&#39;t arrive a bit earlier. What does one do? Well, there is a lot of climbing in Switzerland.. but I only had a few days free before the conference, so instead of trying to meet up with friends, I just headed down to the alps to go walking in the mountains by myself for a couple of days. As a climber, the Eiger has a certain facination for me, so I went to &lt;a href=&quot;http://grindelwald.ch/&quot;&gt;Grindelwald&lt;/a&gt; and then wandered up into the mountains (on a Wanderweg - surprise, surprise ;) Now, what is awesome about the Wanderwegs of Switzerland? Infrastructure. But it is not an infrastructure that is just devoted to trying to keep you safe, not too many rails and boardwalked tracks there... and you can still get into an enourmous amount of trouble if you don&#39;t prepare well... but you are scaffolded in your wandering (more or less as you choose). You can judge your ability and choose your route accordingly, which means that you can also have an amazing time. A choose your own type of &lt;i&gt;personalised&lt;/i&gt; amazing time. I started musing about the wanderwegs as a metaphor for education while I was wandering around from hut to hut... 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		How should we structure our educational system? Should it be safe and well curated?
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/safe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Safe&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		Or should it be wild and a little bit scary?
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wildScary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wild and scary&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		I think that it probably needs to be a little bit of both.
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/safeScary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Safe and scary&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		Perhaps we should stop &quot;looking after&quot; our learners at all... we could just point them in the direction of the mountains and let them wander off to succeed or fail...
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/wanderwegSign.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wanderweg sign&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		Or maybe we just need to show them the way every now and again... 
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/showWay.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wanderweg sign&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		The awesome thing about the Swiss mountains is that the infrastructure lets you do things that would normally be considered very wild in an incredibly safe manner... Thus you can catch a train up to Jungfraujoch and then walk across a glacier! This is not a normal &quot;safe&quot; experience. You are &quot;in the wild&quot; but you are there in a very safe way.
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/safeGlacier.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A safe glacier&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		They also do an impressive job of making the &quot;boring bits&quot; (i.e. the ones that are not essential to the journey) easy... you can persevere if you want, but it is not all that necessary.
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/boringBitsEasy.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;You can make the boring bits easy&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		And you pretty much always get to celebrate your accomplishments at the end of your journey.
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/celebrateAccomplishment1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Celebrate 1&quot; width=&#39;318&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/celebrateAccomplishment2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Celebrate 2&quot; width=&#39;318&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		Now why can&#39;t our learning systems be set up more like that?
	&lt;/p&gt;



</description>
                <link>http://beyondlms.org/blog/18/07/2015/wanderweg</link>
                <guid>http://beyondlms.org/blog/18/07/2015/wanderweg</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-18T00:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>QUT Workshop - Sign-up and requirements elicitation</title>
                <description>
&lt;h6&gt;
	Kirsty Kitto
&lt;/h6&gt;

	In [my last blog](/blog/18/05/2015/UTSworkshop) &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.on.net/~kirsty.kitto/&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; wrote about moving the LA conversation towards a more complex form of analytics. I claimed that I had some pretty good ideas about how to jumpstart the conversation into a position where people really start imagining what is possible.. beyond simple counts and the identification of at risk students.  On 2nd July we held our second workshop, this time at QUT. Here is a photo of Mandy Lupton presenting about halfway through the workshop.
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/QUT-workshop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;QUT workshop&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Instead of holding a day long workshop, I took what I learned at the &lt;a href=&quot;2015-5-18-UTSworkshop.html&quot;&gt;UTS workshop&lt;/a&gt;, and we only scheduled a 2 hour event. One hour to get people understanding what might be possible, and the second hour devoted to requirements elicitation (with free lunch at the end - always essential to get people showing up!) We had a great turn out, with pretty even representation between Academics, Learning Designers and technical people (e.g. IT Services). 
	We had an extra agenda for this day too.. having just obtained ethical clearance to start trials, we were looking to sign up academics who might be interested in volunteering their classes as guniea pigs to try out our current tools in the coming semester of teaching. So we had to find out what exactly they want!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Similar run through as last time, but much more efficient, and we actually had some LA dashboards to show this time! (That got people very excited.) First I gave a background to the project, slightly amended from the UTS workshop, but still pretty much the same:
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;iframe src = &quot;/ViewerJS/#../assets/slides/CLAtoolkit-QUT-Kirsty.pdf&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; height=&#39;540&#39; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	Then &lt;a href=&quot;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/luptonm/&quot;&gt;Mandy Lupton&lt;/a&gt; gave a similar talk too.. this time she used a prezi, which seemed to go down pretty well.
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://prezi.com/embed/k9dkumj7ar5q/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;amp;autoplay=0&amp;amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;amp;landing_data=bHVZZmNaNDBIWjNxWlNQcmg2RlRPRkRDcStneXhHNGR6UzlGVXdVRVhjWkIwdXN0RHY4bk94aTJrZz09&amp;amp;landing_sign=4SQFHEVSePIhMYFnBHurU5DuMbC_l5iGs6X2sE_jHSo#&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; id=&quot;iframe_container&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; width=&quot;635&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	Then the new bit... Simon was not there, so we got Aneesha Bakharia, our Project Manager/Data Analyst to demo the dashboards that she has been developing. These give learners and instructors information about their participation in a Twitter activity (in this case tweeting about the day using the #clatoolkit hashtag) and a Facebook community (in this case a dummy site set up under the CLATest domain). Aneesha was able to show people information about their participation in this exercise in real time. That got people&#39;s attention :) If you want to go and have a look at the current form of the demos then go to &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt; and log in with &lt;i&gt;user: demo &lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;password: clademo&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Having got people&#39;s attention, we then moved onto a split scenario. The technical people got to go and discuss implementation and source code etc. with Aneesha, while Mandy and I got everyone else to start thinking about what more analytics and dashboard capabilities they wanted. We fed them through the following sequence of steps:
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;iframe src = &quot;/ViewerJS/#../assets/slides/CLAtoolkit-QUT-elicitation.pdf&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; height=&#39;540&#39; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;
	Below are some photos of the most interesting ideas that came out.. people were scrawling stuff all over butchers paper, so we got quite a few ideas for the future... Stay tuned!
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/IMG_1131.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ideas1&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/IMG_1132.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ideas2&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/IMG_1135.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Ideas3&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; border=&quot;5&quot;&gt;



</description>
                <link>http://beyondlms.org/blog/02/07/2015/QUTworkshop</link>
                <guid>http://beyondlms.org/blog/02/07/2015/QUTworkshop</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-07-02T00:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>

        <item>
                <title>UTS Workshop: From Data to Visualisation</title>
                <description>
&lt;h6&gt;
	Kirsty Kitto
&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	How do you move the discussion about learning analytics forwards? Sometimes I feel like we are stuck in a rut that leads to the same conversation over and over again:
	&lt;DL&gt;
		&lt;DT&gt;[Kirsty:] What would you like to know about your students?
		&lt;DD&gt;[Academic A:] I want to know how many times they looked at my video.
		&lt;DT&gt;[Kirsty:] Sure, I can do that, but you could have anything! What &lt;i&gt;interesting&lt;/i&gt; things would you like?
		&lt;DD&gt;[Academic B:] I want to know who is in danger of failing and needs help.
		&lt;DT&gt;[Kirsty:] Ok... there are some tools for that. But Learning Analytics can help all students, not just the ones who are at risk. Let&#39;s think about this from another perspective. What would you like your &lt;i&gt;students&lt;/i&gt; to see about their own learning?
		&lt;DD&gt;[Both Academics:] Blank stare.
		&lt;/DL&gt;
	People can&#39;t ask for interesting reports when they don&#39;t know what they could get. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Recently I have been starting to think that the problem is one of &lt;i&gt;analytics literacy&lt;/i&gt;. Counts are easy things to think of, and some people have heard of early intervention systems so they are happy to latch onto that, but it is hard to imagine what you could do with data if you have never seen what it looks like, or learned about how you could manipulate it.
	Indeed, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cshe.unimelb.edu.au/research/teaching/completingtheloop/&quot;&gt;Completing the Loop&lt;/a&gt; OLT project has been finding that people ask for &lt;a href=&quot;http://cshe.unimelb.edu.au/research/teaching/docs/ALASI_presentation.pdf&quot;&gt;remarkably boring things&lt;/a&gt; when we just go out and ask them: &quot;what do you want?&quot;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	So how can we move the conversation forwards?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Last week we tried something different at a workshop that we ran at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uts.edu.au/&quot;&gt;UTS&lt;/a&gt; through with help of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uts.edu.au/research-and-teaching/teaching-and-research-integration/connected-intelligence-centre&quot;&gt;Connected Intelligence Centre&lt;/a&gt;. This was the first event we have hosted as a part of our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.olt.gov.au/project-enabling-connected-learning-open-source-analytics-wild-learning-analytics-beyond-lms-2014&quot;&gt;OLT grant&lt;/a&gt; which is discussed on &lt;a href=&quot;../pages/clatoolkit.html&quot;&gt;other pages&lt;/a&gt; in this site. It was a bit of an experiment in shifting the dialogue forwards, and I am pretty happy with the results. So what did we do?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
	In the one day, we followed a format that went from data to reporting and what I want.. (see &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;the program&lt;/a&gt; for the day, but we only roughly followed it in the end :). Here is a bit more explanation about what we did:
	&lt;dl&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data:&lt;/b&gt;
				We started by introducing people to data. In this case it was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adlnet.gov/capabilities/tla/experience-api.html&quot;&gt;xAPI&lt;/a&gt; data (see also the project &lt;a href=&quot;http://tincanapi.com/&quot;&gt;Tin Can&lt;/a&gt; pages for more information about this data type) but it could have been any format. 
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/dt&gt;
		&lt;dd&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				First we got &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ht2.co.uk/ben/&quot;&gt;Ben Betts&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;http://ht2.co.uk/&quot;&gt;HT2&lt;/a&gt; to give us an introduction to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.curatr3.com/&quot;&gt;Curatr&lt;/a&gt; and his conception of Personal Learning Record Stores based upon &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.learninglocker.org/&quot;&gt;Learning Locker&lt;/a&gt;. 

			&lt;iframe src = &quot;/ViewerJS/#../assets/slides/BenTalk.pdf&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; height=&#39;540&#39; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

			&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				After that &lt;a href=&quot;http://users.on.net/~kirsty.kitto/&quot;&gt;I&lt;/a&gt; gave an introduction to the &lt;a href=&quot;../pages/clatoolkit.html&quot;&gt;CLA toolkit&lt;/a&gt;. I talked about why we are developing it and the kind of data it generates. We had a live demo running which meant that anybody who signed up to our demo and then tried tweeting to #clatest or posting to a test FB group found their data showing up in our demo Learning Record Store (hosted on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://lrs.learninglocker.net/&quot;&gt;LL cloud&lt;a&gt; as a trial account). This really gave people a feel for the type of data that we can capture using the &lt;a href=&quot;../pages/clatoolkit.html&quot;&gt;CLA toolkit&lt;/a&gt;.
			&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;/dd&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;iframe src = &quot;/ViewerJS/#../assets/slides/CLAtoolkit-UTS-Kirsty.pdf&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; height=&#39;540&#39; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;b&gt;Possibilities:&lt;/b&gt;
				Next, we moved into a session that focussed on the possibilities that such data might be able to open up for analytics, both pedagogically and technically. These presentations were really aiming to push people into a more exploratory space.
			&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;dd&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				First, &lt;a href=&quot;http://staff.qut.edu.au/staff/luptonm/&quot;&gt;Mandy Lupton&lt;/a&gt; spoke from her connectivist pedagogical background. As a long time academic &lt;a href=&quot;https://teachinginthewild.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;teaching in the wild&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. beyond the LMS), she is exactly the type of person that we would like to cater for with our project (luckily she is member of the project team :) Mandy introduced a wide range of learning theories and characteristics that we might want to measure and report upon, demonstrating how they relate, and where they are different. 
				&lt;br/&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/dd&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;iframe src = &quot;/ViewerJS/#../assets/slides/CL_presentation_UTS_Mandy.pdf&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; height=&#39;540&#39; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;	
		&lt;dd&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				Then, &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Simon Buckingham Shum&lt;/a&gt; really pushed the envelope of what is possible. Drawing upon his years of working in Learning Analytics, he responded to Mandy&#39;s ideas about what types of things were interesting, showing that many of them could perhaps be measured and reported. One of the things I really appreciated about this talk was how much Simon already &lt;i&gt;had&lt;/i&gt; measured in his life... it really helped push people into a new way of thinking about what Learning Analytics might help them to understand.
				&lt;br/&gt;
			&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;/dd&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;iframe src = &quot;/ViewerJS/#../assets/slides/SBS_CLT_Wkshp_12May2015.pdf&quot; width=&#39;635&#39; height=&#39;540&#39; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;dt&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;
				&lt;b&gt;What do you want?:&lt;/b&gt;
				Only towards the end of the day did we get into asking people what they want. 
			&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/dt&gt;			
		&lt;dd&gt;
			This meant that everyone had been well and truly &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Priming_%28psychology%29&quot;&gt;primed&lt;/a&gt; towards thinking about Learning Analytics in a more interesting way, and I think that the results payed off. We also made sure that everyone thought about what their students might like to see.. in the end Learning Analytics is for learners and if we don&#39;t give our students interesting perspectives on their own learning then I fear we are all wasting our time. Everyone really rose to the challenge, and we all learned a lot. 
		&lt;/dd&gt;
		
	&lt;/dl&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		So, what have I learned? I think that the conversation can get more nuanced and interesting, but it takes serious investment from both sides of the computer science/education divide. Both Learning Analytics people and Pedagogical people need to be at the table, and they all need to engage with the process. No-one should be telling people what they want, but neither should we be accepting that people know what they want at the outset. A lot of people in the workshop kept saying things like &quot;but I doubt you could measure that&quot; only to have someone else pipe up with an example of how they already had, or how you &lt;i&gt;might&lt;/i&gt; be able to. I think that this is a core insight that I took from our workshop. Maybe when people are telling me about the boring things, its because they are censoring their responses by assuming that they know what a computer can&#39;t do, but often people don&#39;t know enough to know what might be possible... its that same old &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GiPe1OiKQuk&quot;&gt;unknown unknowns&lt;/a&gt; problem, which, while it still gives me a giggle to watch Donald go on there, is actually a deep &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Epistemic_modal_logic&quot;&gt;epistemological problem&lt;/a&gt;. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		I also think I have learned enough about what is important that we could now run the priming bits in the space of about an hour. We would do a quick overview of data (making sure there was a demo), follow it with a pedagogical possibilities type of talk that considered what you might be able to do with that data, and finally come back to the types of analytics that have already been done to measure things that were discussed in the pedagogical talk. 
	&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;
		Next time I am definitely trying that...
	&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
                <link>http://beyondlms.org/blog/18/05/2015/UTSworkshop</link>
                <guid>http://beyondlms.org/blog/18/05/2015/UTSworkshop</guid>
                <pubDate>2015-05-18T00:00:00+02:00</pubDate>
        </item>


</channel>
</rss>
